it was a place that was still poor, still segregated, still dramatically in need of change. My school, where I was placed, had no library, no guidance counselor, but it did have a police officer. Half the teachers were substitutes and when students got into fights, the school would send them to the local county jail. This is the school where I met Patrick. He was 15 and held back twice, he was in the eighth grade. He was quiet, introspective, like he was always in deep thought. And he hated seeing other people fight. I saw him once jump between two girls when they got into a fight and he got himself knocked to the ground. Patrick had just one problem. He wouldn't come to school. He said that sometimes school was just too depressing because people were always fighting and teachers were quitting. And also, his mother worked two jobs and was just too tired to make him come. So I made it my job to get him to come to school. And because I was crazy and 22 and zealously optimistic, my strategy was just to show up at his house and say, "Hey, why don't you come to school?" And this strategy actually worked, he started to come to school every day. And he started to flourish in my class. He was writing poetry, he was reading books. He was coming to school every day. Around the same time that I had figured out how to connect to Patrick, I got into law school at Harvard. I once again faced this question, where should I put myself, where do I put my body? And I thought to myself that the Mississippi Delta was a place where people with money, people with opportunity, those people leave. And the people who stay behind are the people who don't have the chance to leave. I didn't want to be a person who left. I wanted to be a person who stayed. On the other hand, I was lonely and tired. And so I convinced myself that I could do more change on a larger scale if I had a prestigious law degree. So I left. Three years later, when I was about to graduate from law school, my friend called me and told me that Patrick had got into a fight and killed someone. I was devastated. Part of me didn't believe it, but part of me also knew that it was true. I flew down to see Patrick. I visited him in jail. And he told me that it was true. That he had killed someone. And he didn't want to talk more about it. I asked him what had happened with school and he said that he had dropped out the year after I left. And then he wanted to tell me something else. He looked down and he said that he had had a baby daughter
era un lugar que aún era pobre, todavía segregado, todavía dramáticamente en necesidad de cambio. Mi escuela, donde fui asignada, no tenía biblioteca, ni consejero, pero sí tenía un oficial de policía. La mitad de los profesores eran suplentes y cuando los estudiantes se metían en peleas, la escuela los enviaba a la cárcel local del condado. Esta es la escuela donde conocí a Patrick. Tenía 15 años y se retrasó dos veces, estaba en octavo grado. Era tranquilo, introspectivo, como metido siempre en un pensamiento profundo. Y odiaba ver pelear a otras personas. Lo vi saltar una vez entre dos chicas cuando se metieron en una pelea y él mismo se tiró al suelo. Patrick tenía un solo problema. No venía a la escuela. Decía que a veces la escuela era demasiado deprimente. porque la gente siempre estaba peleando y los maestros renunciaban. Y su madre tenía dos trabajos y estaba demasiado cansada para hacerlo venir. Así que hice mi trabajo para que viniera a la escuela. Y porque estaba loca y de 22 años y celosamente optimista, mi estrategia fue solo presentarme en su casa. y decir: "Oye, ¿por qué no vienes a la escuela?". Y esta estrategia realmente funcionó, Empezó a venir a la escuela todos los días. Y comenzó a florecer en mi clase. Estaba escribiendo poesía, estaba leyendo libros. Venía a la escuela todos los días. Casi al mismo tiempo que había descubierto cómo conectarme con Patrick, entré en la escuela de derecho en Harvard. Una vez más me enfrenté a esta pregunta, ¿dónde debería ponerme? ¿Dónde pongo mi cuerpo? Y pensé para mí misma. que el Delta del Mississippi era un lugar de donde las personas con dinero, la gente con oportunidad, esas personas, se van. Y las personas que se quedan atrás son las personas que no tienen la oportunidad de irse. No quería ser una persona que se iba. Quería ser una persona que se quedaba. Por otro lado, estaba sola y cansada. Y así me convencí de que podría hacer más cambios. en una escala más grande si tuviera un prestigioso título de abogada. Así que me fui. Tres años despues, cuando estaba a punto de graduarme de la escuela de leyes, mi amigo me llamó y me dijo que Patrick se había metido en una pelea y había matado a alguien. Estaba devastada. Parte de mí no lo creía, pero una parte de mí también sabía que era verdad. Volé hacia allá para ver a Patrick. Lo visité en la cárcel. Y me dijo que era verdad. Que había matado a alguien. Y no quería hablar más de eso. Le pregunté qué había pasado con la escuela y me dijo que había abandonado el año después de que me fui. Y luego quiso decirme algo más. Miró hacia abajo y dijo que había tenido una hija
who was just born. And he felt like he had let her down. That was it, our conversation was rushed and awkward. When I stepped outside the jail, a voice inside me said, "Come back. If you don't come back now, you'll never come back." So I graduated from law school and I went back. I went back to see Patrick, I went back to see if I could help him with his legal case. And this time, when I saw him a second time, I thought I had this great idea, I said, "Hey, Patrick, why don't you write a letter to your daughter, so that you can keep her on your mind?"
que acaba de nacer. Y sintió que la había decepcionado. Eso fue todo, nuestra conversación fue apresurada y torpe. Cuando salí de la cárcel, una voz dentro de mí dijo: "Vuelve. Si no vuelves ahora, nunca volverás". Así que me gradué de la escuela de derecho y volví. Volví a ver a Patrick, Regresé para ver si podía ayudarlo con su caso legal. Y esta vez, cuando lo vi por segunda vez, pensé que tenía esta gran idea, dije, "Oye, Patrick, ¿por qué no le escribes una carta a tu hija, para que puedas tenerla en tu mente?
And I handed him a pen and a piece of paper, and he started to write. But when I saw the paper that he handed back to me, I was shocked.
Y le di un bolígrafo y un trozo de papel, y comenzó a escribir. Pero cuando vi el papel que me devolvió, me quedé impactada.
I didn't recognize his handwriting, he had made simple spelling mistakes. And I thought to myself that as a teacher, I knew that a student could dramatically improve in a very quick amount of time, but I never thought that a student could dramatically regress. What even pained me more, was seeing what he had written to his daughter. He had written, "I'm sorry for my mistakes, I'm sorry for not being there for you." And this was all he felt he had to say to her. And I asked myself how can I convince him that he has more to say, parts of himself that he doesn't need to apologize for. I wanted him to feel that he had something worthwhile to share with his daughter. For every day the next seven months, I visited him and brought books. My tote bag became a little library. I brought James Baldwin, I brought Walt Whitman, C.S. Lewis. I brought guidebooks to trees, to birds, and what would become his favorite book, the dictionary. On some days, we would sit for hours in silence, both of us reading. And on other days, we would read together, we would read poetry. We started by reading haikus, hundreds of haikus, a deceptively simple masterpiece. And I would ask him, "Share with me your favorite haikus." And some of them are quite funny. So there's this by Issa: "Don't worry, spiders, I keep house casually." And this: "Napped half the day, no one punished me!" And this gorgeous one, which is about the first day of snow falling, "Deer licking first frost from each other's coats." There's something mysterious and gorgeous just about the way a poem looks. The empty space is as important as the words themselves. We read this poem by W.S. Merwin, which he wrote after he saw his wife working in the garden and realized that they would spend the rest of their lives together. "Let me imagine that we will come again when we want to and it will be spring We will be no older than we ever were The worn griefs will have eased like the early cloud through which morning slowly comes to itself" I asked Patrick what his favorite line was, and he said, "We will be no older than we ever were." He said it reminded him of a place where time just stops, where time doesn't matter anymore. And I asked him if he had a place like that, where time lasts forever. And he said, "My mother." When you read a poem alongside someone else, the poem changes in meaning. Because it becomes personal to that person, becomes personal to you. We then read books, we read so many books, we read the memoir of Frederick Douglass, an American slave who taught himself to read and write
No reconocí su letra, había cometido simples errores de ortografía. Y pensé que como maestra, sabía que un estudiante podría mejorar dramáticamente en un tiempo muy rápido, pero nunca pensé que un estudiante pudiera retroceder dramáticamente. Lo que incluso me dolió más, fue ver lo que le había escrito a su hija. Había escrito, "Lo siento por mis errores, lo siento por no estar ahí para ti". Y esto era todo lo que sentía que tenía que decirle a ella. Y me pregunté cómo puedo convencerlo de que tiene más que decir, partes de sí mismo de las que no necesita disculparse. Quería que él se sintiera que tenía algo que valía la pena compartir con su hija. Cada día de los siguientes siete meses, lo visité y le llevé libros. Mi bolso de mano se convirtió en una pequeña biblioteca. Llevé a James Baldwin, Llevé a Walt Whitman, CS Lewis. Llevé guías de árboles, de aves, y el que sería su libro favorito, el diccionario. Algunos días, nos sentábamos por horas en silencio, los dos leyendo. Y otros días, leíamos juntos, leíamos poesía. Comenzamos leyendo haikus, cientos de haikus, una obra maestra engañosamente simple. Y le pedía: "Comparte conmigo tus haikus favoritos". Y algunos son bastante divertidos. Así que hay esto por Issa: "No te preocupes, arañas, mantengo la casa casualmente". Y esto: "Duerme la mitad del día, nadie me castigó!". Y esta hermosa, que es sobre el primer día de nieve, "Ciervos que se lamen la primera escarcha de los abrigos del otro". Hay algo misterioso y hermoso. justo como se ve un poema. El espacio vacío es tan importante como las propias palabras. Leímos este poema de WS Merwin, que escribió después de ver a su esposa trabajando en el jardín. y se dieron cuenta de que pasarían el resto de sus vidas juntos. "Déjame imaginar que vendremos otra vez cuando queramos y sea primavera No seremos más viejos que nunca Los desgastados dolores se habrán aliviado como la nube temprana a través de la cual la mañana viene lentamente". Le pregunté a Patrick cuál era su verso favorito, y dijo: "No seremos más viejos que nunca". Dijo que le recordaba un lugar en el que el tiempo simplemente se detiene, donde el tiempo ya no importa Y le pregunté si tenía un lugar así. en el que el tiempo durara para siempre. Y dijo: "Mi madre". Cuando lees un poema junto a alguien más, el poema cambia de significado. Porque se vuelve personal para esa persona, se vuelve personal para ti. Luego leímos libros, leímos tantos libros, Leímos las memorias de Frederick Douglass, Un esclavo estadounidense que aprendió a leer y escribir
and who escaped to freedom because of his literacy. I had grown up thinking of Frederick Douglass as a hero and I thought of this story as one of uplift and hope. But this book put Patrick in a kind of panic. He fixated on a story Douglass told of how, over Christmas, masters give slaves gin as a way to prove to them that they can't handle freedom. Because slaves would be stumbling on the fields. Patrick said he related to this. He said that there are people in jail who, like slaves, don't want to think about their condition, because it's too painful. Too painful to think about the past, too painful to think about how far we have to go. His favorite line was this line: "Anything, no matter what, to get rid of thinking! It was this everlasting thinking of my condition that tormented me." Patrick said that Douglass was brave to write, to keep thinking. But Patrick would never know how much he seemed like Douglass to me. How he kept reading, even though it put him in a panic. He finished the book before I did, reading it in a concrete stairway with no light. And then we went on to read one of my favorite books, Marilynne Robinson's "Gilead," which is an extended letter from a father to his son. He loved this line: "I'm writing this in part to tell you that if you ever wonder what you've done in your life ... you have been God's grace to me, a miracle, something more than a miracle." Something about this language, its love, its longing, its voice, rekindled Patrick's desire to write. And he would fill notebooks upon notebooks with letters to his daughter. In these beautiful, intricate letters, he would imagine him and his daughter going canoeing down the Mississippi river. He would imagine them finding a mountain stream with perfectly clear water. As I watched Patrick write, I thought to myself, and I now ask all of you, how many of you have written a letter to somebody you feel you have let down? It is just much easier to put those people out of your mind. But Patrick showed up every day, facing his daughter, holding himself accountable to her, word by word with intense concentration. I wanted in my own life to put myself at risk in that way. Because that risk reveals the strength of one's heart. Let me take a step back and just ask an uncomfortable question. Who am I to tell this story, as in this Patrick story? Patrick's the one who lived with this pain and I have never been hungry a day in my life. I thought about this question a lot, but what I want to say is that this story is not just about Patrick. It's about us, it's about the inequality between us. The world of plenty that Patrick and his parents and his grandparents have been shut out of. In this story, I represent that world of plenty. And in telling this story, I didn't want to hide myself. Hide the power that I do have. In telling this story, I wanted to expose that power and then to ask, how do we diminish the distance between us? Reading is one way to close that distance. It gives us a quiet universe that we can share together, that we can share in equally. You're probably wondering now what happened to Patrick. Did reading save his life? It did and it didn't. When Patrick got out of prison, his journey was excruciating. Employers turned him away because of his record, his best friend, his mother, died at age 43 from heart disease and diabetes. He's been homeless, he's been hungry. So people say a lot of things about reading that feel exaggerated to me. Being literate didn't stop him form being discriminated against. It didn't stop his mother from dying. So what can reading do? I have a few answers to end with today. Reading charged his inner life with mystery, with imagination, with beauty. Reading gave him images that gave him joy: mountain, ocean, deer, frost.
y que escapó a la libertad por su alfabetización. Había crecido pensando en Frederick Douglass como un héroe, y pensé en esta historia como una de elevación y esperanza. Pero este libro puso a Patrick en una especie de pánico. Se fijó en una historia que Douglass contó sobre cómo, durante la Navidad, los amos daban ginebra a los esclavos como una forma de demostrarles que no podían manejar la libertad. Porque los esclavos tropezarían en los campos. Patrick dijo que se relacionaba con esto. Dijo que hay personas en la cárcel que, como esclavos, no quieren pensar en su condición, porque es muy doloroso. Demasiado doloroso pensar en el pasado, demasiado doloroso pensar en lo lejos que tenemos que ir. Su línea favorita era esta: "¡Cualquier cosa, no importa qué, para deshacerse del pensamiento! Fue este pensamiento eterno de mi condición lo que me atormentó". Patrick dijo que Douglass era valiente por escribir, por seguir pensando. Pero Patrick nunca sabría cuánto se me parecía él a Douglass. Cómo siguió leyendo, a pesar del pánico. Terminó el libro antes que yo, leyéndolo en una escalera de hormigón sin luz. Y luego continuamos leyendo uno de mis libros favoritos, "Galaad" de Marilynne Robinson que es una carta extendida de un padre a su hijo. Le encantó esta línea: "Estoy escribiendo esto en parte para contarte que si alguna vez te preguntaste lo que has hecho en tu vida... tú has sido la gracia de Dios para mí. Un milagro, algo más que un milagro". Algo sobre este lenguaje, su amor, su anhelo, su voz, reavivó el deseo de Patrick de escribir. Y llenó cuadernos y más cuadernos con cartas a su hija. En estas bellas e intrincadas cartas, se imaginaba a él y a su hija yendo en canoa por el río Mississippi. Se imaginaba los dos encontrando un arroyo en la montaña con agua perfectamente clara. Mientras miraba a Patrick escribir, pensé para mí misma, y ahora les pregunto a todos, ¿cuántos han escrito una carta a alguien que sienten que han decepcionado? Es mucho más fácil sacar a esas personas de tu mente. Pero Patrick aparecía todos los días, enfrentando a su hija, responsabilizándose de ella, Palabra por palabra con intensa concentración. Yo queria en mi propia vida ponerme en riesgo de esa manera. Porque ese riesgo revela la fuerza del corazón. Déjenme dar un paso atrás y solo hacerles una pregunta incómoda. ¿Quién soy yo para contar esta historia, como en esta historia de Patrick? Patrick es el que vivió con este dolor y yo no he tenido hambre ni un día en mi vida. Pensé mucho en esta pregunta, pero lo que quiero decir es que esta historia no es solo sobre Patrick. Es sobre nosotros, Se trata de la desigualdad entre nosotros. El mundo de la abundancia del que Patrick y sus padres y sus abuelos han sido excluidos. En esta historia, represento ese mundo de abundancia. Y al contar esta historia, no quería esconderme. Oculta el poder que tengo. Al contar esta historia, quise exponer ese poder. y luego preguntar, ¿cómo disminuimos la distancia entre nosotros? La lectura es una forma de cerrar esa distancia. Nos da un universo tranquilo que podemos compartir juntos, que podemos compartir por igual. Probablemente se estén preguntando ahora qué le pasó a Patrick. ¿Le salvó la vida la lectura? Lo hizo y no lo hizo. Cuando Patrick salió de la cárcel, su viaje fue insoportable. Los empleadores lo rechazaron debido a su historial, su mejor amiga, su madre, murió a los 43 años de enfermedades del corazón y diabetes. Ha estado sin hogar, ha tenido hambre. La gente dice muchas cosas sobre la lectura que me parecen exageradas. Ser alfabetizado no le impidió ser discriminado. No impidió que su madre muriera. Entonces, ¿qué puede hacer la lectura? Tengo algunas respuestas con las que terminar hoy. La lectura cargaba su vida interior con misterio, con imaginación, con belleza. La lectura le dio imágenes que le dieron alegría: montaña, océano, venado, escarcha.
Words that taste of a free, natural world. Reading gave him a language for what he had lost. How precious are these lines from the poet Derek Walcott? Patrick memorized this poem. "Days that I have held, days that I have lost, days that outgrow, like daughters, my harboring arms." Reading taught him his own courage. Remember that he kept reading Frederick Douglass,
Palabras que saben a un mundo libre y natural. La lectura le dio un lenguaje para lo que había perdido. ¿Qué preciosas son estas líneas del poeta Derek Walcott? Patrick memorizó este poema. "Días que he celebrado, días que he perdido, días que crecen, como hijas, mis brazos albergados". La lectura le enseñó su propio coraje. Recuerden que seguía leyendo a Frederick Douglass,
even though it was painful. He kept being conscious, even though being conscious hurts. Reading is a form of thinking, that's why it's difficult to read because we have to think. And Patrick chose to think, rather than to not think.
aunque fuera doloroso. Siguió siendo consciente, a pesar de que la conciencia duele. La lectura es una forma de pensar, por eso es difícil leer porque tenemos que pensar. Y Patrick optó pensar, en lugar de no pensar.
And last, reading gave him a language to speak to his daughter. Reading inspired him to want to write. The link between reading and writing is so powerful. When we begin to read, we begin to find the words. And he found the words to imagine the two of them together. He found the words to tell her how much he loved her. Reading also changed our relationship with each other.
Y por último, la lectura le dio un lenguaje para hablarle a su hija. La lectura lo inspiró a querer escribir. El enlace entre la lectura y la escritura es muy poderoso. Cuando empezamos a leer, empezamos a encontrar las palabras. Y el encontró las palabras para imaginarse a los dos juntos. Encontró las palabras para decirle cuánto la amaba. La lectura también cambió nuestra relación.
It gave us an occasion for intimacy, to see beyond our points of view.
Nos dio una ocasión para la intimidad, para ver más allá de nuestros puntos de vista.
And reading took an unequal relationship and gave us a momentary equality. When you meet somebody as a reader, you meet him for the first time, newly, freshly. There is no way you can know what his favorite line will be. What memories and private griefs he has. And you face the ultimate privacy of his inner life. And then you start to wonder, "Well, what is my inner life made of? What do I have that's worthwhile to share with another?"
Y la lectura tomó una relación desigual y nos dio una igualdad momentánea. Cuando conoces a alguien como lector, te encuentras con él por primera vez, nuevamente, recientemente. No hay manera de que puedas saber cuál será su línea favorita. Qué recuerdos y dolores privados tiene. Y te enfrentas a la máxima privacidad de su vida interior. Y luego empiezas a preguntarte: "Bueno, ¿de qué está hecha mi vida interior? ¿Qué tengo que valga la pena compartir con otro?".
I want to close on some of my favorite lines from Patrick's letters to his daughter. "The river is shadowy in some places but the light shines through the cracks of trees ... On some branches hang plenty of mulberries.
Quiero cerrar con algunas de mis líneas favoritas de las cartas de Patrick a su hija. "El río está en sombra en algunos lugares. Pero la luz brilla a través de las grietas de los árboles... En algunas ramas cuelgan un montón de moras.
You stretch your arm straight out to grab some." And this lovely letter, where he writes, "Close your eyes and listen to the sounds of the words. I know this poem by heart and I would like you to know it, too." Thank you so much everyone. (Applause)
Extiendes el brazo para agarrar unas pocas". Y esta preciosa carta, donde escribe, "Cierra los ojos y escucha los sonidos de las palabras. Conozco este poema de memoria y me gustaría que lo supieras, también". Muchísimas gracias a todos. (Aplausos)